I mean communicated by text a week or
two ago you said that you thought you
might have a genuine chance of becoming
the mayor of Greymouth so that's why I'm
crying everything at it yeah yeah you've
got to balance two things haven't you in
your candidacy for mayor on the one hand
you've got actual responsibilities to
the actual people living there right now
today right that the other and you've
also got a larger responsibility to the
RBE movement because this is a stepping
stone this is a springboard to greater
publicity greater notoriety greater
ability to speak about it in public
right yeah and so you've gotta balance
these two things so to what extent no
let me slightly rephrase that how
seriously are you taking the first part
of that you know your mayoral duties to
the citizens of your town yeah okay I've
known quite a few mayors and we're the
greatest respect to a large degree is a
ceremonial role right they don't
actually have that much executive
authority then another segment of the
board of the council kind of thing yes
you are but you're only the chairman and
you don't have a special casting vote
you have the same valid validity vote as
the other councillors who are all
elected who are most definitely well
embedded locals and you don't have any
influence at tabeling the contents of
what's being discussed
especially here it's extremely
transparent people are very interested
in council activities here I'd say much
more so in UK again everybody knows
everybody it's all much more local much
more familiar with everybody and so the
mayoral role there's not an American
mayor where you know you're allocating
the resources to your Police Department
and school
and so on you know at all
so should you win you would actually be
able to concentrate primarily on role
number two then ie
using it as a platform to publicize RBE
to a wider audience
yeah well of course we've got the money
free party and we've got general
elections in 2020 so that may be a point
of contention for me if I am mayor do I
drop the mayoralty to become a member of
parliament well only if you win all
right you wouldn't have to drop it just
to run would you or would you would you
have to drop it just to run no you don't
have to drop it to run but if you win
you do and by then they'd have to be a
by-election which are expensive and
time-consuming and just annoying and of
course there is a it's happened quite a
few times
the locals well in instances that I've
seen in the past and I guess everyone is
different the locals have been really
pissed off at being abandoned yeah
person might within three understand
that yeah Hobbs
so he's pursuing his own and yeah yeah I
get that on the other hand if you have
the people behind you then it might be
say go on go for it it's only ceremonial
we'll get we can just get another mere
you go on in all the way son you know so
it probably depends on how things are
going at the time just to finish off the
question yeah there are plenty of
mayoral duties cutting ribbons kissing
babies that kind of thing but what the
way I see it because I do like to keep
things succinct if possible believe it
or not the the council machine is a big
cumbersome one of many wheels turning
very slowly and the position of Mayor
really is just part of that machine what
you do have is the ability to direct
that machine so with the right vision
one can point the machine in the right
direction but we're not going to become
a money free town overnight yeah but you
do by bringing people along with you
right not by telling you this is what
we're doing but by convincing
which is how it should be the general
infrastructure in greymouth is all
struggling as well I mean that's
nationwide and I think in the UK to
actually you know under water pipes
sewage tubes etc hope to do about this
crumbling infrastructure I mean what
would you as mayor as well because slash
mayor be able to bring to the table to
solve these problems okay yeah two
answers and this is where it's
absolutely imperative to have the people
on board and depending on how on board
they are depends on which which Road
will travel and I guess it'll probably
end up being a combination of both but
one is if the people are really behind
me and if we've had the RBE conversation
within FP there are two things we could
do we can either go money-free straight
away and fuck it and then because the
revolutionaries are not just the hippies
in the woods and we won't wait for the
central government to provide the money
we'll just go and fucking do it and
there's already a history of there Amer
there are three mayor's on the coast -
by far the biggest one but the most
southern one Bruce Smith is a under
sensor at the moment by the council
overseers because he and a mate when
there's some flood remedial work needed
to be done the hurry they just went out
with their diggers and they're fucking
great big trucks his mate is like 80 and
he owns a big construction company and
they just went out and they just fucking
did it
of course subsequently there was a bill
over 1/2 million dollars for the council
which they then freaked out about
because they hadn't gone through the
transparency but this is the nature of
these Peter no and because again you
know I said everybody throughout the
food chain has been touched by tragedy
these but they're not of a mind to just
wait for central government to come up
with some funding so from this to be
forward and we have a lot of meetings
first but from this day forward we just
will not pay our mortgages rent rates
electricity etc and what are they what
are they actually gonna do because all
the banking here is Australian owned
basically
is the Australian Savings Bank gonna
come here and repossess 10,000 fucking
shacks the middle of no one
what are you gonna do with the mortgages
definitely I love it with the mortgages
and while you're at it and you could
make that argument that was made in the
zeitgeist movie the second one I think
it was that all mortgages are illegal
contracts they are all every single last
one of them fraudulent contract yeah
that's right reminder through the courts
now that's very least you can make a
splash in the papers about it you know
so yeah no I like that but I tell you
what I like the first idea the best
going full RBE straight away I like it
right this is the shit he's doing we've
got the we've got the skill base we've
got them we've got the equipment
whatever you know between us we've got
it let's figure it out man yeah yeah
doing that you're doing that you're in
charge of doing that crack on yeah and
if you don't do it it's your reputation
mate yep yeah and half the beneficiaries
are your Emily so of yours Richard
you've been fighting a good fight for a
while now and you never seem to lose
your appetite through it you never seem
to lose your motivation it's very
impressive
I often I say this but you know one
catches up with lots of different people
not that often and every time I I'm
fascinated by the rhetoric that comes
from conversation rather than from
deliberate study or sort of methodical
development just because most of my work
is talking to people I know I'm amazed
at what comes out and so I love sort of
unscripted conversations where we just
kind of see how we get on and that's
when the good stuff comes out and and
fortunately much of my work in greymouth
is based around having conversations on
the street with ordinary people it's not
high-tech it's not high leverage it's
just sort of face to face one or one or
one on a small group of very organic
conversation and I think that's where
the good stuff is you know it's not
planned it's not intended it's just see
what comes out and I think there's a
subconscious element to that you know
where your subconscious brain is 90
percent of your brain capacity or
something isn't it yeah it's crazy and
if you couldn't access that material
then you'll do a much better job I think
well the things we do access that
material all the time but because we're
so convinced of all there is to us is
our conscious you know our waking
consciousness army you know what I mean
because we're convinced that's all there
is we don't pay attention to our
intuitions and our feelings and our gun
reactions stuff like that and that's
what those things are that's our
subconscious which has access to all of
that additional data it's sending you a
message they don't do that yeah yeah
absolutely yeah I watched a great gavel
mat a lecture the other day where he
said exactly that and how frequently
they are in conflict and he our audience
you know raise your hand if you've ever
had a gut feeling and gone against it
and later regretted it and conversely
how many people have got a gut feeling
gone with it and regretted it and now
hardly any hands what I frequently find
myself saying to people is how is it
going haven't seen you for ages Richard
and with utter sincerity I frequently
say do you know what I think it's going
better than ever more positive sorry
because in answer to question you know
you keep you seem to keep going but I'm
I'm constantly refreshed and sort of
goaded on by the positive results that
we're seeing and and so it just it gets
better and better actually and I'm more
positive and more optimistic now than
I've ever been you know in the last ten
years and I've been up there plenty of
times but I'm it's it's an ever
ascending pathway you know we just seem
to get closer and closer to what we all
what we all aspire to what's the poor
politicians etcetera so they have this
ridiculous balancing act that in the
resource-based economy world we do not
have to play anymore
you just tell the truth
and the science will guide us to the
correct response yeah it's not even
difficult and I was astounded the very
first public outing I made at a mayoral
level when I was contesting their Nelson
mayoral tee in 2013 and I had a lovely
prepared speech and the mayor candidates
got five minutes amount of 450 people in
the audience I mean I was shitting
myself but this is great right I'm going
to talk about spaceship earth but how
it's gonna work in a resource-based
economy and I discovered I mean it's
amazing how you can lose and win in the
same few minutes but I discovered that
scripted speeches with this kind of
material do not work we're not teaching
people anything new
we're d-brane washing them and so
everyone's got their own customs
brainwash and you've got to look them in
the eye and have a conversation of some
sort and figure out where are you stuck
with this what's your personal hang-up
with what i'm proposing because
everyone's got a different version so my
scripted speech was rubbish but when it
came to the questions and answers this
big audience had a lot of questions
about health care about violence about
alcohol in society about jobs pollution
I realized that I had the easiest job of
all and authorized them by far the least
experienced of the four candidates for
the mayoralty I was able to genuinely
put my hand up for every single question
from the audience immediately without
even having to think yeah maybe start
thinking in money-free terms suddenly
every problem we've got becomes easily
soluble yeah
yeah you're free money you're free to
think in terms of like Jaque fresco said
you're out you're free to think in terms
of do we have the technology do we have
the resources do we have the manpower
yes right let's do it is this interest
going to be upset are they gonna let us
through the bonds bla bla bla bla all of
that gone gone advocates of money
however would say that the necessity to
raise finance for a project is a
effective
areas of bad projects not being
undertaken I would say yeah I guess
you're right into a degree in that the
money filters out the crap projects
makes money in which case shit will
happen anyway well that's the thing shit
means now change will not make money no
absolutely absolutely right yeah and
that's the beauty of the resource-based
economy because now you've got a
self-referencing automated process
whereby a the technology assists in the
project so no one has to mix concrete by
hand no one has to dig holes no one has
to hammer nails in anymore I've got
amazing technology to do that so that's
all easy if we want to do something too
easily but you're still gonna need the
well since they buy in I have to look
for a better better worth the investment
still need a better word the money this
might anything goes deep you still need
the involvement of the humans to make it
actually operation you still need the
ability for people to collaborate
collaborate and cooperate on a large
scale I mean no still gonna need to
build things like bridges and tunnels
absolutely hospitals and well maybe
airports but you know whatever whatever
it might be you know there are
large-scale projects which still need to
be undertaken and which affect people
over a large area you know what I mean
and benefit people over a large area but
then there are also people it doesn't
affect and doesn't benefit and so I mean
this is this is where I get a little bit
confused and this is where I have
personally maybe I'm just smart enough
not smart enough to see it I personally
have a problem with detailed transition
plans because from my knowledge of
physics particularly chaotic systems
transition from one equilibrium state to
a different equilibrium state is not
possible without a highly chaotic
turbulent in-between phase and so I kind
of feel that the path to RBE or
something similar to it something that
embraces those philosophies is most
likely going to end up not being
anything that anyone has thought of yet
you know what I mean it's it's something
that will emerge from the collective
when there are enough people working on
the various problems that are that we're
going to encounter and you know what I
mean something will emerge that has
killed yet we don't we do we have no
idea what it looks like now it does take
some Imagineering doesn't it and as
Collinwood put actually Colin Turner
from free world charter who I know I saw
your interview he as he beautifully so
eloquently put to really get this you
have to suspend your disbelief on
several levels at the same time and it
takes quite a lot of mental well
certainly energy to bring that about but
I would say have faith so I'll backtrack
slightly to an interview I did here
actually in 2012 or my birthday
bizarrely with a raya wise reporter from
a newspaper and we they did a big
article and on the money free proposal
and she really liked it me I was really
thrilled you know to get that much
you've got a big chunk of the newspaper
it was fantastic
my first decent outing in the press
really um but and she liked the idea but
she said I think it's gonna take a
massive catastrophe Richard but to bring
this about
and that bugged me I mean this is seven
years ago that's between pitching away
at me for years when I started working
on the west coast which is a very very
different region to the rest of the
country I realized that this major
catastrophe that people I think she was
right had to go through to realize that
something's really got a change and it
may be us that has to change it that
major catastrophe actually doesn't
necessarily need to be shared at the
same time so it may not be a 911 or a
Christchurch mosques shooting it may be
the fact that your daughter took her own
life or your mother died of cancer or
your business collapsed and you lost
your home that is your 911 there
it's your personal catastrophe and
because of the West Coast's precarious
history and position in loads of
different terms nearly everybody there
has been touched by tragedy in some way
whether it's a flood and there's a lot
of social problems there are a lot of
economic challenges and a lot of climate
change challenges and they're very
isolated and they know all about tragedy
we had a horrific mining accident eight
years ago 29 guys died in 2010 and you
know that shouldn't really happen in
21st century mining in a first world
country shouldn't happen anyway but you
know that's unprecedented in the modern
era to have things like that and it
always happens on the west coast so
these people have been through their
massive transformative experience and
thus are ready for change and I've never
said this before don't you think that
that chaos because we are precipitating
a change of mentality nothing else we
just have to change our perspective that
that chaotic period is actually where
many people are now and some of us have
been through earlier than others with
our midlife crisis we could be in that
chaotic period right now and I think I
think actually you make a very good
point that could be exactly what the
explanation is that we are in that right
now and which is what that's Trump
that's brexit that's the rise of the
far-right political correctness and
identity politics everywhere generally
the inability of governments to respond
to even the most basic needs of their
people anymore the example I use in at
the moment if say that the breadwinner
in a household drives a truck for
coca-cola ok those big red trucks and
they carry around 50 tons of coke and
they deliver it to supermarkets and
towns all over the country
and everyone in the family if anyone in
the country knows that those kind of
drinks aren't very good for us but
because of the money thing everybody
write down the food chain you know in
our local dairy there's 19 coca-cola
signs you know just a little country
dairy in Wakefield so it's very very
well promoted although nobody really
wants their children to have it but
nevertheless yeah yeah
and of course right down to the
manufacturing and delivery you know the
person that drives that truck they get
paid to do that and they can thus
provide for their family thank you mummy
or daddy that's how we get the things we
need so we kind of fall well yeah we
would drink it but that's you got makin
gotta do a job you know fair enough but
after money now the family and the
community and the support structure of
that truck driver who he currently
supports with his local contribution
because of the money that he gets from
his job he doesn't need that money
anymore because everything that he used
to buy with it is now supplied for free
so what's the point in going is he gonna
go as a volunteer when a is taking him
away from his family in his community
where he's really wanted as a human
being and be they know they collectively
know that what he's doing is actually
get tremendous society's health as a
whole and they don't need the truck
ready to go away and no one has rotten
teeth anymore yeah but if suddenly he
gets a call and let's say Westport had
an earthquake and they need food they
need blankets they need relief goods and
machinery because of the disasters arson
disastrous situation will that truck
driver get the support of his community
his family his society cause he will and
we've seen evidence of this with the
disasters that happen here every few
months saying that when things go really
really really badly we revert to
communism
[Laughter]
that actually works right brilliant
yeah and the Christchurch earthquakes
prove their enormous Lee I mean the
government completely oh my god what do
we do and we end up with a farm er me
they're called rustic farmers got big
machinery tractors trailers food stores
equipment and they just all these
farmers got together or have a quick
ring round of course they're all related
they all know each other and they got
together with the gear that they needed
to actually help those people out and
then about the same time the student
body you know there's a couple of
universities in Christchurch which you
know after the earthquake there was no
classes the kids well what do we do oh
let's go and help these people and
together with the farmers and all their
equipment they basically took over the
city you know it was incredible and they
went door-to-door you know the place is
covered in mud and there's all these
houses falling down and no electricity
water all over the place these kids went
door-to-door
all right love what do you need you know
wait we're gonna need a tractor over
here to lift this she's gonna need some
food she's got a baby coming and they
sorted it all out and it's amazing and
again a very visit and recent
demonstration of what people do if you
let them you know and that's a really
nice story that's I wasn't aware of that
that's a really really nice story
yeah and everybody remembers it like it
was yesterday man you know uplifting
story isn't it yeah I like to think that
that's that's how we behave most of the
time given the opportunity to do so do
you know what I mean that's that's
that's how I like that's I mean you know
it's not something to prove but that's
what I like to believe that's my art a
good faith here yeah and that's also
part of my chaos interim segment whereby
you know you'll get little opportunities
to dart forward into the future or
what's RBE gonna be like oh we'll hang
on in 2010 2011 we experienced it didn't
we yeah and I mean the volunteering here
is astounding you know if
if you chair a bloody School Committee
in England you get a fucking Gong for it
don't you
we're here he's doing something like
that all the time
and the ambulance service sent John's
ambulance I mean it's the me and
ambulance services 75% voluntary here as
it is the fire service and you know so
people know about volunteering already
and then if it's quite easy just to
extend that so why don't we make your
job voluntary and then people start to
think well what do I do
is it does it contribute anything and
only 27 or 27 percent of all work done
in this country is just managing money
so that they don't actually produce
anything tangible whatsoever
well you're nothing so advertising
marketing sales banking investment
accountancy they're just juggling
numbers and those people can instantly
retire so when they're all we need sorry
what can I do I can retire and of course
you can retire with all the
accoutrements that you gained through
your endeavors previously because you
didn't contribute towards the
manufacture of boats or holiday houses
you had no part in their construction
because that was all done by people who
actually produce things and of course
machines so you can continue to enjoy
your luxury lifestyle but just please
don't go to the office and predate upon
everybody else any making a massive
contribution just by stopping doing
they're incredible and so because it
gets better this is the fantastic thing
about our be when you start think about
it oh my god it's even better than I
thought those people and we all went to
squat there weren't many of my school
but we grew up with them you know which
kids at college and things were the ones
that got into finance and banking and
investment they were the proactive
hard-working motivated intelligent
driven people
and they still are and they do things
that are offensively successful because
it produces great fruits for them
there's nothing you know nothing wrong
with a sparring to that but once we
retire those people they're not just
going to sit around and do nothing
what are they don't weekend's they do
fucking social work and community
restoration and environmental projects
don't they they do those now what are
they going to do in their free with
their networks God the other day art
might I've got a great relationship with
my accountants areia and she's been
basically on board it's pretty amazing
for an accountant for Jesus nearly ten
years what are we gonna because they're
so hard-working these people they're so
proactive and I think they're going to
be a massive part of this because the
accountants know everybody the same
accountant the same person can be
accountant for an environmental group a
church a school a village organization
the government even has accountants you
know a business a marketing company you
know all these things they all associate
through the same accountant frequently
at top level you know at principal level
in the organization so flip over to the
non money world now we're freeing them
up to use their networks so when we have
a I don't know let's say we need a new
sewage system in our remote village I'll
go to my accountant not say where can I
get the money where can I get the
resources to fix the site it's got the
diggers who's got the pious you know and
they hear you talk about because I think
a lot of people in the zeitgeist
movement and The Venus Project and
perhaps in the RDR be a movement in
general see money as an evil and by
extension great anyone who works in the
field of money as being evil so it's
really nice no but it's really nice to
see you thinking that actually they've
got a very valuable real contribution to
making you're quite right to say that in
many cases they are actually the best
and the brightest dollars do go
into these fields and that it would do
well to harness that harness those
energies and intelligence for ya for
better right now absolutely absolutely
no that's really nice to hear I can
understand why you are so successful at
this because you you look to find the
best you know you look to find the best
in people don't see everyone as an asset
rather than anything it's so rewarding
you know because it's sort of win-win
you know you can't really go wrong with
that
yeah it seems to if every every
conversation seems to be positively
contributing you know rather than
goodies and baddies friends and enemies
you know and and it probably is a bit
naive but I do see everybody is just
victims of this system you know and
we've all become horribly corrupted by
it but and especially again sorry on the
west coast where everyone has such a
recent or relevant experience of tragedy
their humanity is that much closer to
the surface and you really don't have to
talk to somebody especially if you are
sincere and impassioned you don't have
to talk to people from very long before
they say yeah you're right mate we've
got to do something yeah whereas me much
of the rest of the country where I've
done a lot of mine so street work it's
frequently the people still think
they're going to be okay this - I know
we're gonna make it all my daughter's
doing great in university my son's got
another business and you know and they
don't they they won't go there you know
the cognitive dissonance is too strong
to dare to penetrate and told me my
within the conversation I had with Nick
the other day that for a lot of people I
said I'm you know I see it a lot in the
UK that kind of person where you know
they've got a lot invested in in their
lives today they've got kids they've got
a career they've got a mortgage they've
got responsibilities they've got a
family they've got a network of friends
they got membership of the club bla bla
bla bla bla you know yeah all beers on
is a long long long way from there it's
a really really really radical shift of
perspective exactly what you said before
that's fundamentally where it is in
perspective and once you've made it you
look back and think well that was really
fucking easy but from the other side a
bit
from the other side of it it's it's not
like that right it's it's it's yeah so
we do need to be infinitely patient and
compassionate with those who are as you
say victims of yeah they're traumatized
ah yeah it's photo 4matic stress
disorder right yeah okay we often
mention gamma left earlier on I'm a
massive fan of his as well he's all yeah
yeah yeah we're in it now it's not
postal my tickets now no but no one you
can't get their intention because
they're sucking in a bunker dodging
bullets you know so they're not going to
listen to a lovely comment almost every
day I mean it's not like it's trauma in
the past and it's over and even right no
it is it's really yeah reinforcing all
the time every day yeah yeah yeah if New
Zealand went money free in September
2020 which is still my kind of favoured
day actually but I do and everything I
all my experience and I don't do much
else reinforces that you know my
background is in big aviation and
engineering and aircraft operations then
we do a lot of trend plotting using
graphs and mathematical models to try
and predict the future so with trend
plotting and what we've been doing with
both I'm going to layer up some graphs
now when you're plotting trends of
social breakdown mental health
challenges environmental challenges all
the things that are going wrong in the
world and if you also same time plot in
the growing awareness of solutions then
you see that they start to coincide at a
point in the future and absolutely
they're exponential and any time you get
near anything exponential it gets really
exciting really quickly yeah and it's
very very important that we don't use
historical precedent to predict future
rate of change you see I don't know that
was intriguing as you've said there
needs to be a period of chaos between
the money world and the no money world
but of course we're gray creatures
aren't we and so we already have a lot
of experience and activity in the know
money world anyway yeah because we don't
charge our dog you know we don't charge
our family for toilet paper and we do a
lot of volunteer work in the community
we if someone falls over in the street
we just help them we go to libraries we
don't own shopping trolleys we just use
them and we take them back we hire cars
we hire hotel rooms you know we're
actually quite used to a sharing type
economy and environment and in fact it's
not as alien as it seems and I don't
think it'll be R in fact I still and I
said this a long time ago I think that
the transformation will be unopposed and
it will be almost effortless actually
and we'll just ease into it overnight
and again we'll be very careful using
historical precedent of change to
predict future change everything's
different in the 21st century and you
know a revolution can be
I think if Jack fresco said a revolution
of consciousness but if that happens
then Australia
you know our nearest neighbor won't have
waited in the 19th century to see what
happens
and of course the rest of the world is
so intimately connected that when a
positive change or indeed a negative one
takes place in one place because of that
technology it can be spread around the
world very quick just give it a quick
example of you know talking about
climate vulnerability let's say
everybody on the planet certainly
anybody of anything like any sort of
influence now is aware of climate
vulnerability all eight billion people
and that news has traveled around the
world in you know probably half of our
lifetimes or less yeah it's gone all
around the world and that's some of the
worst news the manatee has ever had
whereas the prospects of a
resource-based economy is probably the
best news that humanity has ever had in
all of eternity so how long's that going
to take to get around the world and I
can't see the Australian saying don't
know we like our capitalism it's all
great over here in New Zealand they've
suddenly left into a 21st century
utopian paradise like overnight and
they've solved their climate their
health problems their animal welfare
their mental health they solve them
overnight should we do that yep I'll not
not physically but certainly own over
the internet yeah absolutely they they
got a decent kind of target or are they
more climate change no they went they
blocked up various different routes in
central London with placards and boats
and various different themselves to the
front of the Stock Exchange but I
immediately pounced on people say I
don't really want to talk about climate
change and we don't even need to it's
not really relevant at this stage you
know did man cause this etc the the
other day you know just if you're in a
spaceship don't burn the rubbish you
know in in amongst the air that you're
going to breathe and that's all that
really matters there's plenty of other
reasons not to do things that may or may
not claw caused climate harm and and
they're all driven by money at the end
of the day and I always feel these
arguments you know we immediately kind
of get onto a Anti poisons or
anti-abortion or climate change argument
and we we've already lost the point and
we can argue and fall out about it and
send each other emails and build
websites about it
go on protests already miss the point
Jacinda and KO are all in paris patting
each other on the back about what
they're gonna do about the evils in
facebook yeah and they've already missed
the point you know and all that energy
all that angst and dedication will go
into something that's actually a symptom
and not a fuse exactly that word is
attacking symptom enough causes that's
exactly right that's exactly right all
of it and yeah I mean climate change is
just the latest one I tend to agree with
you if we didn't do so fucking stupid
Lee and wastefully then we wouldn't be
having to worry about these things you
know what I've really been up against in
the last 10 years is the sort of
naysayers who have got this position
that oh it's all fine you just need to
work harder you know and the anomalies
that we witness overseas aren't really
real that's just something that happens
in these funny places where they're all
fucked up yeah but it doesn't happen
here and when these things start to
happen here then the few and it's
amazing I said whew the remaining
naysayers who think that it's all going
to be fine and we if you start exporting
coal again and we can still expand dairy
and sell more wine and we're going to
create jobs and we're gonna have green
technologies and green tourism and you
know it's everything's ok those that
relatively small now proportion of the
population is feeling increasingly
isolated now that there's been you know
50 people shot in one incidentally its
television is in and it gets quite easy
to back up you know we need to get
people to think beyond the superficial
ah there's been a shooting ban guns
reaction yeah and ask you know okay just
stop a minute back up I don't think well
why did the guy want to shoot anyone in
the first place why do we have threats
to our climate why do people hunt whales
why do people beat their wives you know
don't just have better surveillance in
houses to prevent you know to catch them
when they do be their wives it's we're
so reactive it's almost child it's worse
than child like actually
but here it's very very obvious because
there's so few people and they're so
intimately connected especially on the
west coast where you know my campaign is
going on and I think there's a much
shorter link between the cause and the
effect of what people are doing whereas
I daresay in Britain or Spain or
something you know bigger more developed
a deeper civilization shall we say
people are much more disconnected from
the root causes of the problems that
they experienced was here they're very
direct so here we see dairy farming
which is our biggest export and that
crops everything up basically the sale
of basically milk powder overseas that
pays for basically everything you know
that's the short version but it's
disastrous for the animals for the
farmers and for the environment and the
water and people know people see that
very clearly and so if we want to
address that those harm things that we
see that you can't eat the food in the
in in the water you can't access farms
anymore because they're all like
electrified prisons you know because a
huge corporate owned now most of these
dairy farms they're not family-friendly
farms that there used to be and it and
the depression and the isolation of the
farmers and their staff is horrific
you know the suicide rate among farmers
is amongst the worst in the country and
they're all going into debt horrific Lee
and of course the product that it
produces isn't even really intended you
know in natural terms for human
consumption anyway so the whole thing is
flawed from start to finish but it's
very easy to point it out here because
we're a relatively shallow civilization
no in that regard that dairy actually
serves no intrinsic purpose except to
get money yeah absolutely and if we it
doesn't actually contribute towards the
manufacture of computers or electricity
or food or dog leads you know
they're completely separate and if we
didn't do dairy that the land and of
course it's all the best land in this
country could basically refer back to
wilderness because we don't need it the
food that New Zealand exports is
extremely expensive I mean even Kiwis
can't afford it so the Bangladeshis
definitely don't get any of it it's very
high high-end very high margin niche
products for rich people not for hungry
people and so that the actual and it and
this is difficult for Kiwis sometimes
the actual produce of New Zealand serves
no genuine purpose on the world table
it's only for rich people it's just to
bring money into it's just to bring
money and just just playing devil's
advocate here I mean obviously I'm on
the same team as you right but just just
for the sake of playing devil's advocate
so what extent does the money that these
that these trades generate and bring
into the country allow New Zealanders to
buy goods from overseas that they might
not otherwise be able to acquire
entirely yeah that's the only way we can
do that and that's once people get to
that stage I tend to especially on the
first conversation I tend to leave them
alone because it's a great if you've got
that far then you're well on the work
well on the road road to seeing that
we're going to be better off without
this money thing so and it's a funny
question actually I really always enjoy
it what about our imports and exports
and there's actually about eight
different answers to that question and
this is where the face-to-face
conversation is so important because if
you're talking to an older person will
say well look in the 1950s when you're
when you came over or when you know when
you were growing up we didn't have
imports at all
we had Morris miners came on a boat
every eight weeks and if you were very
well you could afford one but in fact we
made everything that we need here how
bad was it but it's funny when you
really talk to people they're not even
that sure if we want it anyway again
especially on the west coast where well
they do their laptops well there's a lot
of pushback
it's not brought anything it's not
boring anything tangible and it's not
brought anything good and most people
think of or frequently I get it was
better off before we had them lose you
could talk to people looking down at
they scream yeah I'm not sure I mean I'm
not you know I I have some sympathy for
that view but I'm not sure that's gonna
fly on a global scale I'm full pretty
attached you know laptops and phones
much as there's many awful things about
in particularly in the social media
sphere I mean these things also have the
capacity to be incredibly powerful tools
for good right for education for
information for activity I mean they
they they they can be incredibly
powerful tools for the elevation of the
of the spirit man they don't have to be
destructive I mean I agree they largely
are right now but that's a force of the
way we use them not of their not of the
technology itself yeah yes then I'll say
a leveraging of the negative aspects of
our current system yeah exactly it's in
their interest exactly to have us to
have us jump every time a little message
comes through because it might you know
might be selling us something we want
something that they can convince us that
we won yeah so okay so that has to two
ways of thinking about that a third way
is back in 1803 when New Zealand adopted
enfranchisement voting for women they
didn't worry about what the Saudis would
make of it yeah they thought it was the
right thing to do this probably is the
leading edge of human civilization here
this place and so what we do may seem a
bit out there to house we say less
civilized countries but it may well be
the right thing but we shouldn't wait
for their approval before we do it and
so this is like a spearhead of progress
and there will be unanswered questions
but in the short term we can manage
without brand new iPhones
it's one of the things that makes
country excuse me sort of great and
pivotal actually in what we're doing and
why I think we're gonna succeed in
becoming the first 93 country because of
the original aspirations of the first
settlers and I don't mean the Whalers
and the seal hunters I mean the wealthy
educated and aspirational British mostly
that came in so the late 19th century
they weren't economic refugees they
weren't fleeing terror or persecution
they were looking for a better life in
the nation yeah they were starting to
have second thoughts about the colonial
Imperial March of British aspirations
across the world you know at gunpoint
but they were it was definitely
different when they came to New Zealand
and much of it was to escape the
hierarchy and the class divisions that
were prevalent in you know 19th century
England so we have a few things like the
quarter acre plots no one could build a
house on a site that was smaller than a
quarter of an acre which is enough to
have a pig and a few Chuck's and grow a
few fruit trees kind of thing and
they're still of course they've all been
built there's now 31
a B C and D on every bloody plot you
know in the towns but that that was the
aspiration so that everyone could be
self-sufficient and also things like
access to the countryside and the
waterways particularly is I think called
the queen's chain which means basically
anybody can go anywhere within a chain
you know cricket field length of any
named waterway centre so even when
you're just driving around the
countryside if there's a little creek if
it's got a name then you're allowed to
go into that Creek and hunt and fish and
camp there gather firewood and that's
all over the country and they fiercely
defend that right and that's very very
important to New Zealanders to retain
those freedoms of access and its pioneer
country really they're very resourceful
one of the things that's in tits not
only these disparities these people have
enormous capability you know they're
miners farmers sailors they can do
anything and yet they're fucked because
of this system from outside yeah
they can't even provide for their own
family now despite being capable of
doing anything they can't even provide
for their family because of this fucking
system that says you have to have the
special tokens never mind all the
diggers or the fuel or the chainsaws or
the no no no if you haven't got the
tokens the family start you know and the
wife leads and the kids are on fucking
drugs and that has a lip and you know so
they they hurting like mad because of
this and when I was getting I mean I
generally I've been at work the last
couple of days doing mechanic work and I
tend to wear the same clothes all the
time but on the coast they are
especially anti experts from outside in
suits it sounds to me like I'd like
these West Coast folks yeah you would
yeah they could solid fucking you know
handshake people yeah yeah they really
are
I love going there it's fantastic I just
it's such a boost you know to come every
conversation I come away again further
aren't the scale of holy fucking shit
we're going to do this you know and
that's I'm throwing everything out there
it's funny a dilemma between recruiting
RBE supporters and recruiting voters
those two things well it depends how
long you've got because I wouldn't want
to go in the newspaper for example and
have to in two column inches explaining
this fuckin communist anarchist hippie
from outside fancies being mayor because
they wouldn't put the material across in
a way that was palatable to most people
whereas if I can have a conversation
with those two people then I can
guarantee their vote but you know touch
would basically but it's got to be the
right conversation and it may be as
little as oh I thought what a lovely dog
you know Kay hello what's his name or it
may be 20 minutes of profound anarchism
you know having a proper chair but it's
got to be measured and it's very very
personal so and what I've done in the
past you know through bitter experience
is go too far too soon you know we've
all got these again coming back to the
airplanes analogy where you're doing
everything by performance envelopes you
know you can only do so much
it's the same with humans you know we
can talk about a money free future but
don't say don't go blasting right we're
gonna make everything free tomorrow yeah
okay he's lost it he doesn't have a
rational grip on yeah I kind of don't
like the whole money free I don't like
the name money free party people down
the wrong path of thinking because it's
not really about money free is is not
about taking money away is about
creating a system whereby money no
longer serves a function it's just no
longer has a Pope yeah if you never like
never like to be I mean I'm very very
sensitive to that and I'm just going
outside for a minute so this is I know
if you've seen the bus pictures of it
I've never actually seen the campaign
bus yes
it's all cost a fucking fortune by the
way so this is the number plate is that
is that reverse to you is that the right
way around no that's right that's right
how's the future looking and the website
and this is all IRB East so Institute
resource base there's at the moment
we've got this logo on the side which is
now sort of internationally I'll say
recognized as the money free logo but
not money free party just money free New
Zealand money free France money free USA
well whatever okay and this will when we
get closer to election time it'll say
vote Richard and a special website
we're building called coastwise or NZD
which is specifically for Greymouth and
this particular election is not a global
money briefing at all and then on the
back we've got the whole the big logo
looks great yeah that's really nicely
did yeah now really call out there
called bad boy graphics over in grey
mouth bizarrely yeah so you know been
able to call upon like-minded Souls to
give of their time and work free in
order to help you along I guess you
probably have on some occasions or not
on others right yes some stuff some
stuff no yeah yeah actually bad-boy
graphics are giving us quite a break but
yeah I mean the materials are expensive
for example yeah I put my cup of tea
there have to rewind the video to find
the tea but yes so we're very very
conscious of and cautious with using
terminology but I know I mean I've got a
pocket full of different cards you know
depending on the conversation should I
give them an institute card or a money
free party card or a sticker or a money
free world card I mean again it's the
brainwashing it's not about me it's
about you yeah I liken it to a log jam
you know in a creek that's all jammed up
with logs why doesn't your brain work
clearly and rationally like it was
intended to when you were born you know
a stream should just run and if you can
have a conversation with that person you
can frequently pick out just one or two
logs in that Jam whoosh and they're away
and it can take 10 seconds or it can
take 10 years and then that's but it's
again it's one of the things that drives
me on but especially forgive me on the
coast because these people are so
crushed
they're so fucking downtrodden and
depressed when you come along with
something like this they are a flame you
know and that is a fantastic thing to
behold to be part of that setting people
free again you know and awakening all
that lovely energy and passion and
compassion that's been so shut down for
so long it's a profound experience and
it really drives me along you know which
I guess brings me back to where we
started you know the energy comes from
the people not for me you know I get it
from them you know to see to see people
coming alive it's fantastic to be part
of it privilege actually not that I'm
likening you to Mother Teresa but I
remember seeing him with Mother Teresa
a while ago which she was asked you know
how is it you live in those conditions
and look at all of that suffering year
in year out you know how he's managed to
do that and she said no you don't
understand you know when I when I look
into the faces of these people I see it
is God staring back at me you know what
I mean yeah as far as she's concerned
she's living and exalted like you know
amazed she feels pretty able to do what
she's doing so you know it's yeah again
back to the idea of perspective you know
yeah respect Richard it was a pleasure
really enjoyed that thank you